Matthew Puentes

Local Address 51 Fruit St Apt 2 Worcester, MA 01609 mapuentes@wpi.edu mattpuentes.com 703-615-8072

Permanent Address 705 Fulton Ave Falls Church, VA 22046

EXECUTIVE SUMMARY:

A computer science expert with a focus on cybersecurity, as well as experience in network security, team leadership, independent work, goal setting, and requirement gathering. As a leader in the field, is adept at working in group settings, identifying achievable objectives, and moving between high-level thinking and low-level technological knowhow.

EDUCATION:

Worcester Polytechnic Institute, Worcester, MA

GPA 3.86, May 2021

- Bachelor of Science in Computer Science.
- Master's Degree in Computer Science.

George Mason High School, Falls Church, VA

GPA 3.69, June 2016

• Advanced Diploma.

Thomas Nelson Community College, Hampton, VA

• Dual Enrolled through NASA's VASTS program.

GPA 4.00, Nov. 2015

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE:

Digital Design & Imaging Service Inc., Falls Church, VA

Engineering Intern, June 2016 – Aug. 2016

- Maintained and developed aerial photography equipment.
- Used Photoshop and other professional image and location mapping software to assist in large-scale landscape architecture analysis projects such as crowd counts.
- Worked for diverse clientele, from construction firms to large cities.
- Worked 32 hours a week.

Junior Engineer, June 2017 – Aug. 2017

- Designed, implemented, and maintained software to process GPS and photography data.
- Maintained and upgraded electronic and mechanical systems for aerostat photography.
- Fulfilled duties of above position when required.
- Worked 32 hours a week.

ID Tech, Falls Church, VA

Counselor June 2018 – Aug. 2018

- Supervised and taught a classroom of 9-10 children in STEM related fields.
- Worked 40 hours a week.

George Mason Technology Help Desk, Falls Church, VA

Computer Technician

Sept. 2014 – June 2016

- Diagnosed and repaired hardware and software issues with school-owned equipment.
- Worked with Apple and Microsoft computers and software, gaining familiarity with both systems.
- Coached students and teachers in the usage of school hardware and software.
- Worked 8 hours a week.

PROJECTS:

Assistant Lead Software Engineer for Software Engineering Course Worcester, MA *Mar.* 2018 – May 2018 This was a course I took at WPI, which had ten-person student teams working in a class competition to apply Agile development methodologies and software design patterns in Java to create an indoor pathfinding application, map builder, and integrated service request modules for Brigham & Women's main hospital campus. The software systems that student teams created were to inform Brigham & Women's Hospital about potential features, user interfaces, or design approaches that they might consider implementing.

- As an assistant lead software engineer, I helped gather software requirements by survey, interview, and brainstorming. I also helped create user stories, scenarios and storyboards.
- I designed and wrote the path visualization and map node editing subsystems of the application through the creation of UML use case, class, sequence, and activity diagrams. I was the technical leader of the entire map editing and code.
- As an assistant project manager, I was jointly responsible for managing project tasks, coordinating the team, and keeping all of the members motivated.
- Our team successfully delivered the requested application at the end of the seven-week term. The team was recognized for:
 - Winning the team competition for best application in the first development iteration.
 - Winning the team competition for best feature in the second and third development iteration for custom node mapping with intuitive selection, and a neural network that predicted 2D to 3D hospital map conversion.

Head programmer for FIRST robotics team, Falls Church, VA

Sept. 2013 – June 2016

- FIRST robotics is a program in which students in high school design, code, and build a working robot according to a specified challenge in a 2-month timeframe.
- The program has regional, state, and national levels with leading robotics experts acting as judges.
- While I was programming lead, our team successfully placed first at the regional and state level, as well as being a finalist on the national level.
- I spent 150+ hours a year programming, designing, testing, and piloting the robot.

Windows expert for Cyber Patriots team, Falls Church, VA

Sept. 2014 – June 2016

- Cyber Patriots is a government-run program where students are given an operating system with security variabilities and have to try and solve as many as possible under a time limit.
- I was in charge of the Windows OS, which ranged from Windows 10 to Windows Server 2009.
- I was challenged to quickly and efficiently find and eliminate security threats ranging from firewall settings to malicious software, which I was able to accomplish via a thorough checklist and process created in the off-season
- Our team placed first in the state of Virginia.

RELEVANT COURSEWORK

- Software Engineering (as described above)
 - o Under Prof. Wilson Wong
 - o Grade Received: A
- Database Systems
 - o Under Prof. Wilson Wong
 - o Grade Received: A
- Algorithms
 - O Under *Prof. Suzanne Mello-Stark*
 - o Grade Received: A
- Operating Systems
 - o Under Prof. Hugh Lauer
 - o Grade Received: A
- Machine organization and assembly language
 - o Under <u>Prof. Michael Ciaraldi</u>
 - o Grade Received: A
- Computer Networks
 - o Under *Prof. Yanhua Li*
 - o Grade Received: A
- Network Security
 - o Under Prof. Craig Shue
 - o Grade Received: A

ACCOLADES & HONORS:

- Worcester Polytechnic Institute Honor Roll, 2016, 2017, 2018
- Worcester Polytechnic Institute Charles O. Thompson Scholar, 2017
- Cyber Corps Scholarship for Service Recipient, 2018

SKILLS:

- **Programming Languages:** Java, JavaDB, JavaFX, MySQL, Python, C++, C, SQL, Lua, LISP
- Software: GitHub, Microsoft Office, Bash/Unix Shell, IntelliJ, Eclipse, Gradle, TravisCI, Vim
- Interpersonal: Proven leadership and teamwork skills, experience with agile development

ACTIVITIES:

- **FIRST Robotics**, George Mason High School, 2011-2017
- Cybersecurity CTF challenges, Various, 2015 Present
- **Beta Theta Pi**, WPI, December 2016 Present
 - o Vice President, December 2017 March 2017
 - o Financial Chair, April 2018 October 2018
 - o Vice President, December 2018 Present